Benjamin Franklin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Benjamin Franklin Papers 1726-1907 (bulk 1770-1789)
MSS21451
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
8,000 items
40 containers
12 linear feet
12 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Statesman, publisher, scientist, and diplomat. Correspondence, journals, records, articles, and other material relating to Franklin's life and career. Includes manuscripts (1728) of his Articles of Belief and Acts of Religion; negotiations in London (1775); letterbooks (1779-1782) of the United States legation in Paris; records (1780-1783) of the United States peace commissioners, including journals kept by Franklin and Richard Oswald; and papers (1781-1818) of Franklin's grandson, William Temple Franklin (1760-1823).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John, 1735-1826--Correspondence.; Bache, Richard, 1737-1811--Correspondence.; Carmichael, William, approximately 1739-1795--Correspondence.; Cushing, Thomas, 1725-1788--Correspondence.; Dumas, Charles Guillaume Frédéric, 1721-1796--Correspondence.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790. Articles of belief and acts of religion. 1728; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823. William Temple Franklin papers.; Hartley, David, approximately 1731-1813--Correspondence.; Hewson, M. S. (Mary Stevenson)--Correspondence.; Ingenhousz, Jan, 1730-1799--Correspondence.; Jay, John, 1745-1829--Correspondence.; Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792--Correspondence.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834--Correspondence.; Lansdowne, William Petty, Marquis of, 1737-1805--Correspondence.; Laurens, Henry, 1724-1792--Correspondence.; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806--Correspondence.; Oswald, Richard, 1705-1784. Richard Oswald papers.; Sartine, Antoine de, comte d'Alby, 1729-1801--Correspondence.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de, 1719-1787--Correspondence.; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Correspondence.; Whitefield, George, 1714-1770--Correspondence.; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Continental Congress.; United States. Legation (France) U.S. Legation (France) letterbooks. 1779-1782.; United States. Postmaster General.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--France.; Postal service--United States.
Places
France--Foreign relations--United States.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1775-1783.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Peace.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.
Titles
Benjamin Franklin Papers at the Library of Congress; Definitive Treaty of Peace Between Great Britain and the United States (1783 September 3)
Occupations
Diplomats.; Publishers.; Scientists.; Statesmen.
Provenance
The papers of Benjamin Franklin, statesman, publisher, scientist, and diplomat, were given to the Library of Congress by transfer, gift, and purchase, 1903-1968. An addition was transferred from the Library of Congress archives to the collection in 1989.
Additional Guides
The papers have been described in Benjamin Franklin, A Register and Index of His Papers in the Library of Congress (Manuscript Division Reference Department: Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. 1973) and in the Library's publication List of the Benjamin Franklin Papers in the Library of Congress compiled in 1905 by Worthington C. Ford. An index of selected correspondence is available in the Manuscript Division Reading Room and as a PDF document.
Related Material
Franklin correspondence can also be found in other collections in the Manuscript Division of the Library, including the Peter Force Collection and the papers of George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, Edmond Charles Genet, James McHenry, Silas Deane, and Andrew Ellicott. Other Franklin items in the Library are in the Mrs. Archibald Crossley Autograph Collection, the J. Pierpont Morgan Book of Signers, the Gaston Tissandier Collection, and the reproductions from archives in Great Britain ( Public Record Office ) and France ( Ministère des Affaires Etrangères ).
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Benjamin Franklin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on twelve reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The papers of Benjamin Franklin are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000064.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1706, Jan. 17 Born, Boston, Mass.
1718 1723 Apprenticed as a printer to his brother James Franklin
1725 1726 Journeyman printer, London, England
1727 Founded the Junta, a debating club, Philadelphia, Pa.
1728 Wrote Articles of Belief and Acts of Religion
1729 Purchased Pennsylvania Gazette
1730 Married Deborah Read Rogers (died 1774)
1731 Established the Library Company of Philadelphia, Pa.
1732 1758 Published Poor Richard, 1732-1747, and Poor Richard Improved, 1748-1758, commonly known under collective title Poor Richard's Almanack
1736 1751 Clerk, Pennsylvania Assembly
1740 Invented the Pennsylvania fireplace (Franklin stove)
1743 Proposed formation of the American Philosophical Society
1751 Founded with others, the Academy for Education of Youth (now University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.) Founded Philadelphia City Hospital, Philadelphia, Pa. Published letters to Peter Collinson, Experiments and Observations on Electricity. London: Printed and Sold by E. Cave
1751 1764 Represented Philadelphia at the Pennsylvania Assembly
1754 Represented Pennsylvania at the Albany Congress
1757 1762 Political agent of the Pennsylvania Assembly, London, England
1766 Reappointed as agent for Pennsylvania, London, England
1771 Began autobiography
1775 Left London, England, for Massachusetts Elected member of the Second Continental Congress Named postmaster general
1776 Served on committee to draft the Declaration of Independence Went to France as one of three American commissioners to negotiate a treaty
1778 Negotiated treaties of commerce and defense with France Appointed sole plenipotentiary in France
1781 Appointed with John Jay and John Adams to negotiate a peace with Great Britain
1783 Signed Treaty of Paris with Great Britain and asked Congress for his recall
1785 Returned to the United States
1785 1788 President, Supreme Executive Council of Pennsylvania
1787 Represented Pennsylvania at the Constitutional Convention
1790 Signed memorial to Congress as last official act as president of the Pennsylvania Society for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery
1790, Apr. 17 Died, Philadelphia, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Benjamin Franklin (1706-1790) span the years 1726 to 1907, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1770-1789. Consisting of correspondence, journals, records, articles, and other material, the collection reflects Franklin's many interests and activities.
Series I relates chiefly to Franklin's mission to France to obtain diplomatic recognition of the rebellious colonies as well as financial and military aid and to participate in the peace negotiations in Paris and London preceding the Treaty of Paris in 1783. The series contains seventeen interrelated volumes chiefly pertaining to Franklin's years in France. Six are letterbooks of the United States legation in Paris, 1779-1782. Other volumes include letters in French to Franklin, 1777-1780; records of the peace commissioners, 1780-1783; negotiations in London, 1775 (original and Franklin's corrected transcript); and Franklin's correspondence with David Hartley, 1775-1781. Single volumes include the Craven Street, London, letterbook, 1772-1773, one of the few pre-Revolutionary Franklin letterbooks to survive; the signed Petition of the First Continental Congress to the King, 16 October 1774; and Richard Oswald's journal concerning the peace commission, 1782.
Series II has been described in the Library's publication List of the Benjamin Franklin Papers in the Library of Congress compiled in 1905 by Worthington C. Ford. Of the fourteen volumes in this series, eleven represent a selection of Franklin's correspondence, 1726-1790 made by William Temple Franklin prior to his departure for London in 1791. The letters bear many editorial annotations, deletions, and other changes made by William Temple Franklin before publication of his three-volume work. This series also contains a volume of notes entitled “Medical, Nature Printing and Addenda” and two volumes of William Temple Franklin's papers.
Series III represents a miscellaneous group of Benjamin Franklin items gathered by the Library. It includes the original manuscript of Franklin's Articles of Belief and Acts of Religion; his correspondence with M. S. Hewson, 1760-1779; a facsimile copy of his ledger as postmaster general, 1775-1778; his correspondence with Jan Ingenhousz, 1777-1785; and other papers, 1728-1841 and undated.
Series IV includes copies of items held by other institutions and transcripts of material from Series I and II which is not on the microfilm of the Library's Benjamin Franklin Papers.
The Addition consists of a letter, 1753, from Franklin to George Whitefield concerning the importance of “good works” in the Christian faith. The letter written in an unknown hand is a print made from a microfilm in the American Philosophical Society Library, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five series:
Series I, 1772-1783
Series II, 1726-1818
Series III, 1728-1841
Series IV, 1744-1907.
Addition, 1753
Container List
- Series I, 1772-1783 (Box 1-16, Reel 1-4)
  Letterbooks, journals, records of negotiations, a petition, and correspondence.
  Indexed by name of writer or recipient.
  - Records of the United States legation, Paris, France (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Letters in French to Franklin, 1777-1780 (vol. 1)
    - Letterbooks (Box 2, Reel 1)
      - 1779 (vol. 2)
      - 1779-1780 (vol. 3) (Box 3, Reel 1)
      - 1780 (vol. 4) (Box 4, Reel 1)
      - 1781 (vol. 5) (Box 5, Reel 2)
      - 1781 (vol. 6) (Box 6, Reel 2)
      - 1782 (vol. 7) (Box 7, Reel 2)
    - Peace commissioners (Box 8, Reel 2)
      - 1780-1783 (vol. 8)
      - 1780-1783 (vol. 8a) (Box 8a, Reel 2)
    - Commissioners to France, 1776-1779 (vol. 9) (Box 9, Reel 2)
  - Petition of the Continental Congress to the King, Philadelphia, Pa., 1774, Oct. 26 (vol. 10) (Box 10, Reel 3)
  - Craven Street letterbook, London, England, 1772-1773 (vol. 11) (Box 11, Reel 3)
  - Oswald, Richard, journal, peace commission, 1782 (vol. 12) (Box 12, Reel 3)
  - Franklin's journal, peace commission, 1782 (vol. 13) (Box 13, Reel 3)
  - Negotiations in London, England, 1775 (Box 14, Reel 4)
    - Original autograph (vol. 14)
    - Transcript corrected by Franklin (vol. 15) (Box 15, Reel 4)
  - Correspondence with David Hartley, 1775-1781 (vol. 16) (Box 16, Reel 4)
- Series II, 1726-1818 (Box 17-30, Reel 5-12)
  General correspondence and miscellaneous papers of Benjamin Franklin and correspondence and other papers of William Temple Franklin.
  - 1726, July 22-1774, May 21 (vol. 17) (Box 17, Reel 5)
  - 1774, June 10-1777, Sept. 4 (vol. 18) (Box 18, Reel 5)
  - 1777, Sept. 7-1778, Oct. 9 (vol. 18) (Box 18, Reel 6)
  - 1778, Oct. 20-1781, May 1 (vol. 19) (Box 19, Reel 6)
  - 1781, May 4-1782, Jan. (vol. 20) (Box 20, Reel 7)
  - 1782, Jan.-1784, Jan. 6 (vol. 21) (Box 21, Reel 7)
  - 1784, Jan. 12-1785, May 23 (vol. 22) (Box 22, Reel 8)
  - 1785, May 26-1786, Dec. 10 (vol. 23) (Box 23, Reel 8)
  - 1786, Dec. 15-1789, Mar. 2 (vol. 24) (Box 24, Reel 9)
  - 1789, Apr.-1790, undated (vol. 25) (Box 25, Reel 9)
  - Undated (vol. 26) (Box 26, Reel 10)
  - Miscellaneous material in French, 1778-1786, undated (vol. 27) (Box 27, Reel 10)
  - Medical, Nature Printing and Addenda, 1781-1785, undated (vol. 28) (Box 28, Reel 10)
  - Franklin, William Temple, papers (Box 29, Reel 11)
    - Correspondence, 1781-1818, undated (vol. 29)
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous material, 1814-1818, undated (vol. 30, pt. 1) (Box 30, Reel 11)
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous material, 1814-1818, undated (vol. 30, pt. 2) (Box 30, Reel 12)
- Series III, 1728-1841 (Box 31-32, Reel 12)
  Literary and scientific articles, memoranda, correspondence of Benjamin Franklin and William Temple Franklin, and miscellany.
  Arranged chronologically and indexed by name of writer and recipient.
  - Miscellaneous material (Box 31, Reel 12)
    - 1728-1783 (vol. 31)
    - 1784-1841, undated (vol. 32) (Box 32, Reel 12)
- Series IV, 1744-1907 (Box 33-39)
  Copies of correspondence and miscellaneous material from collections outside the Library of Congress.
  Arranged chronologically and indexed by name of writer and recipient. Transcripts of material from Series I and II are unarranged and unindexed.
  - Reproduction and miscellaneous material (Box 33)
    - 1744-1775
    - 1776-1907, undated (Box 34)
    - Unarranged transcripts (Box 35-39)
- Addition, 1753 (Box 39)
  Copy of a letter from Franklin to George Whitefield.
  - Letter (copy), Benjamin Franklin to George Whitefield, 1753 (Box 39)